Guide to the William H. O'Brien Collection
Erie Canal Museum
William H. O'Brien Collection
1904 - 1914
Papers of William H. O'Brien from the New York State Department of Public Works.
6 boxes
O'Brien, William H., 1861-1942
Erie Canal Museum 318 Erie Boulevard East Syracuse, NY 13202
The collection is open for research use.
William H. O'Brien (1861-1942) was employed by the New York State Department of Public Works for many years. In 1911, he was appointed Superintendent of Repairs for Section 6 of the Erie Canal, which extended from Canastota to Camillus and from Syracuse to Lock 5 on the Oswego Canal. Working from his office in the Weighlock Building in Syracuse, Mr. O'Brien oversaw the maintenance and repair of the entire Section 6, including the supervision of scow and carpenter forces, bank watchmen, bridge tenders, feeder tenders, and locktenders. In 1912, O'Brien was promoted to Assistant Superintendent of Public Works for the MIddle Division of the Erie Canal.
Erie Canal (N.Y.); Syracuse (N.Y.); New York (State). Department of Public Works
This collection includes correspondence and business documents of William H. O'Brien from his tenure with the New York State Department of Public Works, during the years 1904-1914. These papers were recovered from Mr. O'Brien's family home in Baldwinsville, NY in 1996.
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1904-1910
    - Correspondence-1909, June 18, 1909; Includes item 1996.1.03 (Box 1, Folder Correspondence-1909)
    - Correspondence-March 24, 1904, Includes item 1996.1.04 A+B (Box 1, Folder Correspondence-March 24, 1904)
  - Correspondence 1911
    - Correspondence-Jan.-Mar. 1911, January, 1911 - March, 1911; Includes items 1996.1.05-.14 (Box 1, Folder Correspondence-Jan.-March 1911)
    - Correspondence-Apr.-June 1911, April, 1911 - June, 1911; Includes items 1996.1.15-.50 (Box 1, Folder Correspondence-Apr.-June 1911)
    - Correspondence-July-Sept. 1911, July, 1911 - September, 1911; Includes items 1996.1.51-.83 (Box 1, Folder Correspondence-July-Sept. 1911)
    - Correspondence-Oct.-Dec. 1911, October, 1911 - December, 1911; Includes items 1996.1.84-.123 (Box 1, Folder Correspondence-Oct.-Dec. 1911)
    - Letter from Mary Comerford to Margaret, 1911, February 19, 1911; Includes item PC 2002.5.1 (Box 5, Folder O'Brien Papers)
  - Correspondence 1912
    - Correspondence-Jan.-Mar. 1912, January, 1912 - March, 1912; Includes items 1996.1.139-.170 (Box 2, Folder Correspondence-Jan.-Mar. 1912)
    - Correspondence--Political, April 29, 1912, Includes item 1996.1.171 (Box 2, Folder Correspondence--Political, April 29, 1912)
    - Correspondence-Apr.-June 1912, April, 1912 - June, 1912; Includes items 1996.1.172-.234 (Box 2, Folder Correspondence-April-June 1912)
    - Correspondence-July-Sep. 1912, July, 1912 - September, 1912; Includes items 1996.1.235-.296 (Box 2, Folder Correspondence-July-Sep. 1912)
    - Correspondence-Aug. 21, 1912, August 21, 1912; Includes item 1996.1.297 (Box 2, Folder Correspondence-Aug. 21, 1912)
    - Correspondence-Oct.-Dec. 1912, October, 1912 - December, 1912; Includes items 1996.1.298-.326 (Box 2, Folder Correspondence-Oct.-Dec.1912)
    - Correspondence-Dec. 21, 1912, December 21, 1912; Includes item 1996.1.327 (Box 2, Folder Correspondence-Dec. 21, 1912)
    - Correspondence-Syracuse Rendering Co., 1912, November 22, 1912; Includes items PC 1999.10.32-.33 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Syracuse Rendering Co., 1912)
    - Correspondence-Regarding Gift for Duncan Peck, 1912, Includes items PC 1999.10.35.1-.3 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Regarding Gift for Duncan Peck, 1912)
  - Correspondence 1913
    - Correspondence-Jan.-Mar. 1913, January, 1913 - March, 1913; Includes items 1996.1.371-.392 (Box 3, Folder Correspondence-Jan.-Mar. 1913)
    - Correspondence-Apr.-June 1913, April, 1913 - June, 1913; Includes items 1996.1.393-.417 (Box 3, Folder Correspondence-Apr.-June 1913)
    - Correspondence-Reference for William Conlon 1913, June 2, 1913; Includes item 1996.1.418 (Box 3, Folder Correspondence-Reference for William Conlon 1913)
    - Correspondence-July-Sep. 1913, July, 1913 - September, 1913; Includes items 1996.1.419-.441 (Box 3, Folder Correspondence-July-Sep. 1913)
    - Correspondence-Oct.-Dec. 1913, October, 1913 - December, 1913; Includes items 1996.1.442-.465 (Box 3, Folder Correspondence-Oct.-Dec. 1913)
    - Letter to Wm. O'Brien from his son, 1913, March 13, 1913; Includes item PC 2002.5.2 (Box 5, Folder O'Brien Papers)
    - Correspondence-Bridges, 1913, Includes items PC 1999.10.31.1-.2 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Bridges, 1913)
    - Correspondence-Car Advertisement, 1913, February 22, 1913; Includes items PC 1999.10.37.1-.2 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Car Advertisement, 1913)
  - Correspondence 1914
    - Correspondence-Jan.-Mar.1914, January, 1914 - March, 1914; Includes items 1996.1.482-.491 (Box 4, Folder Correspondence-Jan.-Mar. 1914)
    - Correspondence-Apr.-June 1914, April, 1914 - June, 1914; Includes items 1996.1.492-.511 (Box 4, Folder Correspondence-Apr.-June 1914)
    - Correspondence-July-Sep. 1914, July, 1914 - September, 1914; Includes items 1996.1.512-.529 (Box 4, Folder Correspondence-July-Sep. 1914)
    - Correspondence-Oct.-Dec. 1914, October, 1914 - December, 1914; Includes items 1996.1.530-.568 (Box 4, Folder Correspondence-Oct.-Dec. 1914)
    - Correspondence-Rome Locomotive and Machine Works 1914, December 14, 1914; Includes item 1996.1.569 (Box 4, Folder Correspondence-Rome Locomotive and Machine Works 1914)
    - Letter to Mrs. O'Brien from her son, 1914, May 20, 1914; Includes item PC 2002.5.3 (Box 5, Folder O'Brien Papers)
    - Correspondence-Rental of State Land, 1914, June 20, 1914; Includes item PC 1999.10.19 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Rental of State Land, 1914)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Correspondence-Misc. Letters to O'Brien, 1910-1913, Includes items PC 1999.10.9.1-.9 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Misc. Letters to O'Brien, 1910-1913)
    - Correspondence-Misc. Letters to O'Brien, 1912-1914, Includes items PC 1999.10.39.1-.14 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Misc. Letters to O'Brien, 1912-1914)
    - Correspondence-Misc. Letters to O'Brien, 1911-1913, Includes items PC 1999.10.22.1-.9 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Misc. Letters to O'Brien, 1911-1913)
- Maintenance/Repairs
  - Maintenance/Repairs 1911
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Black River Canal, 1911, Includes items 1996.1.126-.128 (Box 1, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Black River Canal, 1911)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Winter Estimate, 1910-1911, Includes item 1996.1.129 (Box 1, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Winter Estimate, 1910-1911)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Summer Estimate, 1911, Includes item 1996.1.130 (Box 1, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Summer Estimate, 1911)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Winter Schedule, 1911-1912, Includes item 1996.1.131 (Box 1, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Winter Schedule, 1911-1912)
    - Correspondence-Regarding Bridge, Sec. 6, 1911, May, 1911; Includes items PC 1999.10.4 A-C (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Regarding Bridge, Sec. 6, 1911)
    - Correspondence-Complaint About Canal Leakage, 1911, June 15, 1911; Includes item PC 1999.10.15 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Complaint about Canal Leakage, 1911)
    - Correspondence-Sec. 5 Bridges, 1911, Includes items PC 1999.10.34.1-.8 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Sec. 5 Bridges, 1911)
  - Maintenance/Repairs 1912
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Bridges, Sec. 5 1912, May 13, 1912; Includes items 1996.1.328-.329 (Box 2, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Bridges-Sec. 5)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Middle Division, 1912, Includes item 1996.1.330 Estimate of lumber required for repairs on middle division (Box 2, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Middle Division, 1912)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Middle Division, 1912, Includes items 1996.1.331-.332 Estimates of work required on canal (Box 2, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Middle Division, 1912)
    - Report-List of Materials to Paint Bridges, 1912, Includes item PC 1999.10.1 (Box 6, Folder Report-List of Materials to Paint Bridges, 1912)
    - Correspondence-Bridge at Jack's Reef, 1912, December 14, 1912; Includes item PC 1999.10.8 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Bridge at Jack's Reef, 1912)
    - Report-NYS Canal Specifications, 1912, Specifications relating to the furnishing and delivering of timber and plank for use in the canals of the state of New York.; Includes item PC 1999.10.11 (Box 6, Folder Report-NYS Canal Specifications, 1912)
    - Correspondence-Regarding Canal Leakage, 1912, May 6, 1912; Includes item PC 1999.10.18 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Regarding Canal Leakage, 1912)
  - Maintenance/Repairs 1913
    - Maintenance/Repairs-placing needles at lock #2, 1913, Includes items 1996.1.467 A-C (Box 3, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-placing needles at lock #2, 1913)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Rome R.R. Bridge, 1913, Includes items 1996.1.362-.370 (Box 3, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Rome R.R. Bridge, 1913)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Lumber Inventory, 1913, Includes items 1996.1.468-.471 (Box 3, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Lumber Inventory, 1913)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Winter Schedule, 1912-1913, Includes item 1996.1.472 (Box 3, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Winter Schedule, 1912-1913)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Summer Schedule, 1913, Includes item 1996.1.473 (Box 3, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Summer Schedule, 1913)
    - Correspondence-Yorkville Bridge Repairs, 1913, April, 1913; Includes item PC 1999..10.5 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Yorkville Bridge, 1913)
    - Correspondence-Solvay Bridge Work, 1913, June 2, 1913; Includes item PC 1999.10.6 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Solvay Bridge, 1913)
    - Correspondence-Morris Machine Works, 1913, February 24, 1913; Includes items PC 1999.10.17.1-.4 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Morris Machine Works, 1913)
  - Maintenance/Repairs 1914
    - Lumber Required-Middle Division, 1914, Includes item 1996.1.574 (Box 4, Folder Lumber Required-Middle Division, 1914)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Summer Schedule, 1914, Includes items 1996.1.575-.579 (Box 4, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Summer Schedule, 1914)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Middle Division Winter Schedule, 1913-1914, Includes item 1996.1.580 (Box 4, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Middle Division Winter Schedule, 1913-1914)
    - Correspondence-Cazenovia Canning Co. Regarding Bridge, 1914, June 11, 1914; Includes item PC 1999.10.7 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Cazenovia Canning Co. Regarding Bridge, 1914)
    - Report-Blueprint of Dam #1, Cayuga and Seneca Canal, 1914, October 28, 1914; Includes items PC 1999.10.16.1-.2 (Box 6, Folder Report-Blueprint of Dam 1, 1914)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Winter Schedule, 1914, Includes item PC 1999.10.28 (Box 6, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Winter Schedule, 1914)
  - Maintenance/Repairs, undated
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Bridges, Includes item 1996.1.595; Reports on conditions of bridges (Box 5, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Bridges)
    - Maintenance/Repairs, undated, Includes items 1996.1.596-.602, .609, .619-628 (Box 5, Folder Miscellaneous-undated)
    - Report-Work to be done on Bridges, Sec. 5, Includes item PC 1999.10.3 (Box 6, Folder Report-Work to be done on Bridges)
    - Maintenance/Repairs-Black River Canal, Includes item PC 1999.10.10.1-.2 (Box 6, Folder Maintenance/Repairs-Black River Canal)
    - Report-Lumber Required, Middle Division, Includes item PC 1999.10.27 (Box 6, Folder Report-Lumber Required, Middle Division)
- Personnel
  - Personnel 1911
    - Personnel, 1911, Includes item 1996.1.133. Appointment letters for positions on Sec. 6, Erie Canal (Box 1, Folder Personnel, 1911)
  - Personnel 1912
    - Personnel, 1912, Includes items 1996.1.344-.345 List of employees and list of new appointments for 1912 (Box 2, Folder Personnel, 1912)
    - Personnel-Roster of Employees, Middle Division, 1912, Includes item 1996.1.346 (Box 2, Folder Personnel-Roster of Employees, Middle Division, 1912)
    - Personnel-Middle Division Employees, 1912, Includes item 1996.1.347 (Box 2, Folder Personnel-Middle Division Employees, 1912)
    - Petition-George DeWitt, 1912, March 28, 1912; Includes item 1996.1.348 Petition by the Democratic County Committeemen in Sullivan, NY to appoint George DeWitt as Head Gate Tender at Chittenango Landing. (Box 2, Folder Petition-George DeWitt, 1912)
    - Petitions for Appointments, 1912, Includes items 1996.1.349-.354 (Box 2, Folder Petitions for Appointments, 1912)
    - Personnel-Campaign Contributions, 1912, Includes items 1996.1.650-.666 (Box 5, Folder Personnel-Campaign Contributions, 1912)
  - Personnel 1913
    - Personnel, 1913, Includes items 1996.1.474-.478 (Box 3, Folder Personnel, 1913)
    - Personnel-Middle Division, 1913, Includes item 1996.1.669 (Box 5, Folder Personnel-Middle Division, 1913)
  - Personnel, undated
    - Petitions for appointments-Cayuga and Seneca Canals, Includes item 1996.1.629 (Box 5, Folder Petitions for appointments-Cayuga and Seneca Canals)
    - Personnel, undated, Includes items 1996.1.630-.644 (Box 5, Folder Personnel)
    - Personnel-Oswego Canal, Includes items 1996.1.645-.646 (Box 5, Folder Personnel-Oswego Canal)
    - Personnel-Miscellaneous undated, Includes items 1996.1.603-.618 (Box 5, Folder Miscellaneous-undated)
    - Personnel-Middle Division, Includes item PC 2002.5.4 (Box 5, Folder O'Brien Papers)
    - List of Employees in Middle Division, Includes item PC 2002.5.4 (Box 5, Folder O'Brien Papers)
    - Department of Public Works Application, Includes items PC 1999.10.21.1-.2 (Box 6, Folder Application Blank-Dept. Public Works)
    - Personnel-List of Employees, Sec. 5, Includes items PC 1999.10.23.1-.2 (Box 6, Folder Personnel-List of Employees, Sec. 5)
    - Personnel-List of Employees, Includes items PC 1999.10.24.1-.2 (Box 6, Folder Personnel-List of Employees)
  - Personnel 1914
    - Personnel-Campaign Contributions, 1914, Includes item 1996.1.667 (Box 5, Folder Personnel-Campaign Contributions, 1914)
    - Personnel-List of Appointments, Cayuga and Seneca Canal, 1914, Includes items PC 1999.10.20.1-.2 (Box 6, Folder Personnel-List of Appointments, Cayuga and Seneca Canal, 1914)
- Reports
  - Reports, 1911
    - Bridges, Includes items 1996.1.01-.02. Lists of bridges on the Erie Canal (Box 1, Folder Bridges)
    - Inventory of Machine Shop, 1911, Includes items 1996.1.124-.125 (Box 1, Folder Inventory of Machine Shop, 1911)
    - Report-Expenditures of the Canals, 1911, Includes item PC 1999.10.38 (Box 6, Folder Report-Expenditures of the Canals, 1911)
  - Reports, 1913
    - Inventory-Middle Division, 1913, February 24, 1913; Includes item 1996.1.466 Inventory of material, tools, and equipment on the Middle Division. (Box 3, Folder Inventory-Middle Division, 1913)
  - Reports, 1914
    - Lockmaster's Reports, 1914, Includes items 1996.1.573 A-D (Box 4, Folder Lockmaster's Reports, 1914)
    - Report-Lockmaster's Reports, 1914, Includes items PC 1999.10.12.1-.4 (Box 6, Folder Report-Lockmaster's Reports, 1914)
  - Reports, undated
    - Location of Boats, Includes item 1996.1.594 (Box 5, Folder Report-Location of Boats)
    - Report-List of Cables on Bridges, Includes item PC 1999.10.2 (Box 6, Folder Report-List of Cables on Bridges)
    - Report-Contract "B", Record showing position of gates at guard lock together with elevation of water above and below the lock.; Includes item PC 1999.10.13 (Box 6, Folder Report-Contract "B")
- Financial Documents
  - Bonds
    - Bonds, 1912, Includes items 1996.1.134-.138 (Box 2, Folder Bonds 1912)
    - Bonds, 1913, Includes items 1996.1.355-.361 (Box 3, Folder Bonds, 1913)
    - Bonds, 1914, Includes items 1996.1.479-.481 (Box 4, Folder Bonds, 1914)
  - Receipts
    - O'Donnell's Grill Receipts, 1912, July, 1912; Includes Items 1996.1.333-.339 (Box 2, Folder O'Donnell's Grill Receipts, July 1912)
    - Receipts-Newspaper, 1914, Includes items 1996.1.581-.593 Receipts for the Syracuse Herald, made out to O'Brien at the Canal Office. (Box 4, Folder Receipts-Newspaper, 1914)
    - Receipts-Syracuse Herald, 1913-1914, Includes items PC 1999.10.25.1-.31 (Box 6, Folder Receipts-Syracuse Herald, 1913-1914)
- Permits
  - Permits 1912
    - Permit-Syracuse Cold Storage, 1912, February 15, 1912; Includes item 1996.1.340 (Box 2, Folder Permit-Syracuse Cold Storage, Feb. 15, 1912)
    - Permit-Railroad, 1912, March 29, 1912; Includes item 1996.1.341 (Box 2, Folder Permit-Railroad, March 29, 1912)
    - Permit-Telephone Co. Contract, 1912, March 14, 1912; Includes item 1996.1.342 (Box 2, Folder Permit-Telephone Co. Contract, March 14, 1912)
    - Permit-Watson Wagon Co., Canastota, 1912, April 8, 1912; Includes item 1996.1.343 (Box 2, Folder Permit-Watson Wagon Co., Canastota, April 8, 1912)
- Miscellaneous
  - Newspaper Articles
    - Newspaper-Canal Abstract, June 1911, Includes item 1996.1.132 Abstract of Expenditures by W.H. O'Brien, Superintendent of Repairs upon the Erie Canal. Lists employees and salaries. (Box 1, Folder Newspaper-Canal Abstract, June 1911)
    - Newspaper Clipping-Water Supply, News article titled "No Concession, O'Brien Claims", about water supply disagreement between Canal Officials and the city of Skaneateles.; Includes item 1996.1.670 (Box 5, Folder Newspaper Clipping-Water Supply)
    - Miscellaneous Material Relating to Rev. Hendricks, 1914, Includes items PC 1999.10.30.1-.6; Newspaper articles and letters relating to Rev. Hendricks (Box 6, Folder Miscellaneous Material Relating to Rev. Hendricks, 1914)
  - Political Documents
    - Petition-William Kelley, 1912, Petition by the Democratic Party in unknown city to elect William Kelley as State Committeeman.; Includes item 1996.1.668 (Box 5, Folder Petition-Wm. Kelley, 1912)
    - Political Letter-'Bull Moose', Satirical letter signed Dooley, to Friend Hennessy, about the upcoming election. No date; Includes item 1996.1.649 (Box 5, Folder Letter-Political "Bull Moose")
    - Correspondence-Democratic Congressional Committee, 1913, Includes items PC 1999.10.36.1-.2 (Box 6, Folder Correspondence-Democratic Congressional Committee, 1913)
  - Business Documents
    - Miscellaneous-Business Files, 1912 - 1913; Includes items PC 1999.10.14.1-.8 (Box 6, Folder Miscellaneous-Business Files)
    - Miscellaneous-Papers from O'Brien's Desk, 1911-1914, Includes items PC 1999.10.26.1-.17 (Box 6, Folder Miscellaneous-Papers from O'Brien's Desk, 1911-1914)
    - Miscellaneous Documents, Includes items PC 1999.10.40.1-.3 (Box 6, Folder Miscellaneous Documents)
- Legal Documents
  - Lawsuits
    - Lawsuit-State St. Bridge, 1914, June 6, 1914; Includes item 1996.1.570 (Box 4, Folder Lawsuit-State St. Bridge, 1914)
    - Lawsuit-Water Pipe Break, Weighlock Bldg., 1914, June, 1914; Includes items 1996.1.571-.572 (Box 4, Folder Lawsuit-Water Pipe Break, Weighlock Bldg. 1914)
    - Claims Against State, 1914, Includes items PC 1999.10.29.1-.5 (Box 6, Folder Claims Against State, 1914)
- Photographs
  - Photographs of William O'Brien
    - Photo-O'Brien at Desk, Includes item 1996.1.647 (Box 5, Folder PHoto-O'Brien at Desk)
    - Photo-O'Brien, Mercer Milling, Lock 24, 1911 - 1914; Includes item 1996.1.648 (Box 5, Folder Photo-O'Brien, Mercer Milling, Lock 24)